1909 Hudson-Fulton Celebration Collection
Marist College Archives and Special Collections
- 8. Badges, Medals, and Pins, 1909; 12.0 linear feet 12 Box (Box 10 -, Box 22)
  - Subseries 8.2: Pins, 1909; 2.0 linear feet 2 Box (Box 21, Box 22)
    - Hudson Fulton Celebration Portrait Button Pin #1-2, Paper on back stained. Tear in center of paper on back on one pin. Metal is tarnished. (Box 21)
      Button pin featuring portraits of Hudson and Fulton and images of “Half-Moon” and “Clermont” in four squares. Outer edges of image are metallic gold. Maker’s mark on back contains Trades Council Union label. Button reads “Hudson-Fulton Celebration/ 1609-1909”.
    - Hudson Fulton Celebration Twisted Edge Portrait Pin, Metal frame is tarnished. Backing paper is faintly stained. (Box 21)
      Metal backed pin featuring portraits of Hudson and Fulton and images of “Half-Moon” and “Clermont” in four squares. Outer frame made of twisted metal. Button reads “Hudson-Fulton Celebration/ 1609-1909”.
    - Hudson Fulton Celebration Braided Edge Portrait Pin, Metal tarnished and metal backing rusted. (Box 21)
      Metal backed pin featuring portraits of Hudson and Fulton and images of “Half-Moon” and “Clermont” in four squares. Outer frame made of braided metal. Button reads “Hudson-Fulton Celebration/ 1609-1909”.
    - Hudson Fulton Celebration Circular Portrait Button Pin #1-4, Metal on each is tarnished. One pin without backing paper rusted and has cracks over front image. (Box 21)
      Button pin featuring circular portraits of Hudson and Fulton above images of “Half-Moon” and “Clermont”. Three of four have backing paper featuring the different novelty locations they were purchased. Outer edges of image are metallic gold. Button reads “Hudson-Fulton Celebration/ Sept. 5 To Oct. 9”.
    - Small Hudson Fulton Celebration Circular Portrait Button Pin #1-2, Metal tarnished. One pin has ribbon attached. (Box 21)
      Small, button pin featuring circular portraits of Hudson and Fulton above images of “Half-Moon” and “Clermont”. Both have backing paper featuring the different novelty locations they were purchased. Outer edges of image are metallic gold. Button reads “Hudson-Fulton Celebration/ Sept. 5 To Oct. 9”.
    - Small Fulton Portrait Button Pin, Metal tarnished and metal backing rusted. (Box 21)
      Small, button pin featuring portrait of Fulton beside “Clermont”. Outer edges of image are metallic gold. Button reads “Hudson-Fulton Celebration/ 1609-1909”.
    - Clermont on Hudson Button Pin, Metal is tarnished and metal backing is rusted. (Box 21)
      Button pin featuring color image of Clermont on Hudson River. Button reads “Hudson-Fulton Celebration/ Up The Hudson 1807”.
    - HF General Commemorative Exercises Button Pin, Metal tarnished. Potential wax along back outline and on backing paper. (Box 21)
      White button pin reading “Hudson-Fulton/ Celebration/ Commission/ General/ Commemorative/ Exercises”. Backing paper maker’s mark contains Trades Council Union label.
    - Troy, NY HF Celebration Button Pin, Metal tarnished. Stain on upper right of backing paper. (Box 21)
      Button pin featuring portraits of Hudson and Fulton on coins above color images of “Half-Moon” and “Clermont”. Button reads “Troy, N.Y./ Oct. 7-9-1909.”
    - First National Bank HF Celebration Button Pin, Stain on right of backing paper. Metal is tarnished. Rusting along edges of metal. (Box 21)
      Button pin featuring portraits of Hudson and Fulton on coins above color images of “Half-Moon” and “Clermont”. Button reads “Compliments of The First National Bank/ Hudson, N.Y., October 1-9,1909.”
    - Gilded Hudson Portrait Pin, Some plating from around the edges has worn away. Small stains along bottom of backing paper. Metal on back is tarnished. (Box 21)
      Plated metal button pin featuring color portrait of Henry Hudson. Button reads “Hudson-Fulton Celebration 1909”.
    - Small Hudson Fulton Celebration Circular Braided Edge Portrait Button Pin, Metal is tarnished. Backing paper is stained and has a tear in right side. (Box 21)
      Button pin featuring circular portraits of Hudson and Fulton above images of “Half-Moon” and “Clermont”. Button reads “Hudson-Fulton Celebration/ Sept. 5 To Oct. 9”. Outer frame made of braided metal.
    - Black White Fulton Portrait Button Pin, Back pin is missing. Most of backing paper is missing, though edges are still attached. Metal is tarnished. Backing metal is rusted. Small stain on front upper left. (Box 21)
      Button pin featuring black and white portrait of Fulton on front.
    - Small Fulton Coin Button Pin, Back pin is missing. Backing paper is faintly stained. Metal is tarnished. (Box 21)
      Small, button pin featuring image of Fulton on face of coin.
    - Hudson and Fulton Color Portrait Button Pin, Metal is tarnished. Edges of front image have begun to lift away from metal backing. (Box 21)
      Small, button pin featuring color portraits of Henry Hudson and Robert Fulton. Button reads “Hudson-Fulton Celebration 1909.”
    - Hudson and Fulton Color Portrait Braided Edge Button Pin, Edges of backing metal have begun to rust. Metal is tarnished. (Box 21)
      Small, button pin featuring color portraits of Henry Hudson and Robert Fulton. Button reads “Hudson-Fulton Celebration 1909.” Edge of button made of braided metal.
    - Half-Moon New York Celebration Ribbon and Coin Pin, Ribbon is fraying around edges and contains small stains across front. Metal of pins has tarnished. Patina across both faces of “Half-Moon” portion of pin. (Box 21)
      Metal pin in the shape of “Half-Moon” attached to New York Hudson-Fulton Celebration coin and tri-colored ribbon. Ribbon colors of Dutch flag. Small, brass coin features portraits of Hudson and Fulton on obverse. Reverse reads “New York/ Sept. 25-Oct. 2/ 1909. Obverse reads “Hudson-Fulton/ 1609/ 1807/ Celebration. Small hole punched in top center.
    - Anchor Fulton Pennant Pin, Small spots of tarnish on upper right of obverse. (Box 21)
      Small, brass pin featuring a life-preserver ring and anchor overlaid with red and white pennant reading “Robert Fulton”.
    - Hendrick Hudson Namesake Ship Pin, Slight discoloration of metal. Small chain on reverse of pin attached to nothing. (Box 21)
      Small, scalloped-edge, metal pin featuring image of “U.S.S. Hendrick Hudson”.
    - Hendrik Hudson Half-Moon Pin, Brooch on back missing. Tarnish across front and back. (Box 21)
      Half-moon shaped pin reading “Hendrik Hudson”.
    - HF Lord’s Prayer Eagle Pin #1-2, Very small spots of tarnish in various places on both pins. (Box 21)
      Brass pin in shape of eagle attached to HF Lord’s Prayer Coin. Brass coin features portrait of Hudson and Fulton on obverse. Obverse reads “Hudson-Fulton/ Celebration/ NY 1909”. Reverse features “The Lord’s Prayer” in its entirety. Hole punched in top center.
    - Half-Moon New York Celebration Coin Pin, Slight toning across reverse of coin. Slight tarnish along brooch of pin. Small area of patina where brooch connects to reverse of pin. (Box 21)
      Metal pin in the shape of “Half-Moon” attached to New York Hudson-Fulton Celebration coin. Small, brass coin features portraits of Hudson and Fulton on obverse. Reverse reads “New York/ Sept. 25-Oct. 2/ 1909. Obverse reads “Hudson-Fulton/ 1609/ 1807/ Celebration. Small hole punched in top center.
    - Brass Bordered Lord’s Prayer Coin Pin, Spots of tarnish along brass border on both faces. Top bar and brooch missing. (Box 21)
      Pin featuring medal coin depicting portrait of Hudson and Fulton on obverse. Obverse reads “Hudson-Fulton/ Celebration/ NY 1909”. Reverse features “The Lord’s Prayer” in its entirety. Coin is bordered by an intricately designed brass border. Reverse of border reads “Schwaab S. & S. Co., Milwaukee, Wis.”
    - HF Tercentenary Celebration Eagle Pin, Both pin and coin are tarnished across both faces. Slight patina on reverse of eagle in center. Dark spot of tarnish on coin obverse lower left. (Box 21)
      Medal pin in the shape of eagle attached to coin featuring portraits of Hudson and Fulton along with images of “Half-Moon” and “Clermont” on obverse. Reverse of coin reads “Souvenir/ Hudson-Fulton/ Tercentenary/ Celebration/1609-1807-1909/ New York.”
    - HF Lord’s Prayer Eagle Pin #3, Small spots of dark tarnish in various places on both pins. (Box 21)
    - HF Small Portrait Button Pin With Suspended Clermont Figurine, Metal of figurine is tarnished. Faint toning across all sides. Large area of potential corrosion across reverse side of ship. (Box 21)
      Small, button pin featuring color portraits of both Hudson and Fulton above images of “Half-Moon” and “Clermont”. Outer edges are golden. Pin is attached to a purple ribbon. Small, metal figurine of “Clermont” is suspended at bottom. Sides of figurine read “Clermont.” Maker’s mark on reverse of pin for W.F. Miller.
    - HF Large Portrait Button Pin With Suspended Clermont Figurine, Small stain on bottom of obverse of ribbon. Ribbon is frayed along edges. Metal of figurine tarnished. (Box 21)
      Small, button pin featuring color portraits of both Hudson and Fulton above images of “Half-Moon” and “Clermont”. Outer edges are golden. Pin is attached to a dark blue ribbon. Metal figurine of “Clermont” is suspended at bottom. Sides of figurine read “Clermont” and each feature a functioning paddle wheel. Maker’s mark on reverse of pin for J. Boller Novelties and Carnival Goods.
    - HF Small Portrait Button Pin With Suspended Clermont Figurine #2, Ribbon is discolored and fraying all along the left edge and has begun to separate from top pin. Metal of figurine tarnished in several areas. (Box 21)
      Small, button pin featuring color portraits of both Hudson and Fulton above images of “Half-Moon” and “Clermont”. Pin is attached to a red ribbon. Small, metal figurine of “Clermont” is suspended at bottom. Sides of figurine read “Clermont.” Maker’s mark on reverse of pin for W.F. Miller.
    - HF Small B&W Portrait Button Pin With Suspended Clermont Figurine, Ribbon is fraying along edges. Metal of figurine is tarnished. Chips and indentations along bottom edge of figure. Backing metal of pin is rusted. (Box 21)
      Small, black and white button pin featuring portraits of Hudson and Fulton below banner for Hudson-Fulton Celebration. Small, metal figurine of “Clermont” suspended from pin by ribbon. Tri-colored ribbon features colors of Dutch flag. Sides of figurine read “Clermont”.
    - HF Celebration Portrait and Ships Pin With Suspended Clermont Figurine, Potential copper plating is worn and tarnished on all sides. Bottom edges have been pressed together. (Box 21)
      Button pin featuring portraits of Hudson and Fulton and images of “Half-Moon” and “Clermont” in four squares. Outer edges of image are metallic gold. Button reads “Hudson-Fulton Celebration/ 1609-1909”. Metal figurine of “Clermont” suspended from pin with red ribbon.
    - Half-Moon and Champlain Pin, Orange of ribbon has faded and edges are beginning to fray. Coin and metal backing of pin have tarnished. (Box 22)
      Button pin featuring orange ribbon attached to Discovery of Lake Champlain coin. Top button depicts black and white image of “Half-Moon” overlaid with small portrait of Hudson. Bottom coin obverse features portrait of Samuel de Champlain on obverse. Reverse features image of Champlain discovering Lake Champlain above image of New York State coat of arms and pine tree. Obverse reads “1609/ 1909/ Champlain”. Reverse reads “The Tercentenary Of The Discover Of Lake Champlain”.
    - Hudson-Fulton Celebration Eagle Pin, Metal of pin and medal tarnished. The suspension ring has begun to come apart. (Box 22)
      Metal pin in the shape of an eagle with medal for Hudson-Fulton Celebration attached. Medal features images of “Half-Moon” and “Clermont”. Medal reads “1609/ Hudson Fulton/ Celebration/ 1909”.
    - HF Lord’s Prayer Eagle Ribbon Pin, Ribbon is discolored. Tarnish on both pin and coin. Reverse center of coin has large spot of patina. Thread at center of ribbon has begun to come undone. (Box 22)
      Brass pin in shape of eagle attached to HF Lord’s Prayer Coin and tri-colored ribbon. Ribbon is the colors of Dutch flag. Brass coin features portrait of Hudson and Fulton on obverse. Obverse reads “Hudson-Fulton/ Celebration/ NY 1909”. Reverse features “The Lord’s Prayer” in its entirety. Hole punched in top center.
    - Hudson-Fulton Centennial Ribbon Button Pin, Ribbon is discolored. Bottom edges of ribbon have frayed. Thread of reverse has frayed at end. Stain along left edge of red portion of bottom ribbon tails (Box 22)
      Button pin featuring portraits of Hudson and Fulton above banner with dates of Hudson-Fulton Celebration, September 25-October 2, 1909. Below portraits button features images of “Half-Moon” and “Clermont”. Top reads “Hudson-Fulton/ Centennial/ New/ York”. Backing ribbon is tri-colored featuring the colors of the Dutch Flag.
    - Hudson Fulton Celebration Circular Portrait Ribbon Pin, Ribbon is discolored. Top and bottom edge of ribbon fraying. (Box 22)
      Button pin featuring circular portraits of Hudson and Fulton above images of “Half-Moon” and “Clermont” and tri-colored ribbons. Ribbons colors of Dutch flag. Three of four have backing paper featuring the different novelty locations they were purchased. Outer edges of image are metallic gold. Button reads “Hudson-Fulton Celebration/ Sept. 5 To Oct. 9”.
    - Hudson Fulton Celebration Portrait Ribbon Pin, Backing ribbon discolored. All edges of ribbon frayed. Blue portion of top ribbons completely frayed. Blue tail ribbon missing. Ribbon fragile. (Box 22)
      Button pin featuring portraits of Hudson and Fulton and images of “Half-Moon” and “Clermont” in four squares. Backing ribbon is tri-colored featuring colors of Dutch flag. Outer edges of image are metallic gold. Maker’s mark on back contains Trades Council Union label. Button reads “Hudson-Fulton Celebration/ 1609-1909”.
    - Tri-Color Scalloped Hudson-Fulton Portrait Pin, Ribbon frayed along top and bottom edges. Ribbon is severely discolored. Ribbon is very fragile. Very slight discoloration across obverse of pin. (Box 22)
      Small, brass pin featuring scalloped edges and tri-colored border. Border features colors of Dutch flag, as does backing ribbon. Center of pin features portraits of Hudson and Fulton.
    - Scalloped, Brass Edge Hudson-Fulton Portrait Pin, Most of backing ribbon missing. Ribbon is severely discolored and frayed. Ribbon is fragile. Obverse top left edge of border is missing. Metal backing of pin is rusted. Small stain on obverse right center. (Box 22)
      Button pin featuring black and white portraits of Hudson and Fulton below banner for Hudson-Fulton Celebration in 1909. Outer, scalloped edges brass with intricate design. Tricolored backing ribbon features colors of Dutch flag.
    - HF Clermont Up The Hudson Button Pin, Metal backing severely rusted and rust is showing through color image on front of button. Brooch is completely patinaed. Portion of backing edge missing on upper left. (Box 22)
      Button pin featuring color image of Fulton’s “Clermont” on the Hudson River. Obverse reads “Hudson-Fulton Celebration/ Up The Hudson 1807.”
    - HF Large B&W Portrait Button Pin With Suspended Clermont Figurine, Ribbons are discolored and fraying along edges. Metal of figurine is tarnished. Backing metal of pin is rusted. (Box 22)
      Large, black and white button pin featuring portraits of Hudson and Fulton below banner for Hudson-Fulton Celebration. Small, metal figurine of “Clermont” suspended from pin by ribbon. Suspension is orange and two backing ribbons are white and orange.
    - Small Metal Clermont Figurine, Toning on all sides of figurine, including both top and bottom. Potentially missing pin. (Box 22)
      Small, metal figurine of Fulton’s “Clermont”. Sides of figurine read “Clermont” and each feature a functioning paddle wheel.
- 9. Fobs, 1909; 1.0 linear feet 1 Box (Box 23)
  Various commemorative watch fobs created to commemorate The 1909 Hudson-Fulton Celebration.
  - HF Celebration Silver-Plated Half-Moon Watch Fob, A large portion of silver-plating has worn away on both sides of fob. Small area of tarnish on front bottom and top back. Dark tarnish on base metal. (Box 23)
    Silver-plated watch fob featuring image of Hudson’s “Half-Moon”. Lettering reads “Hudson Fulton/ Celebration/Half Moon/ New York/ 1609/ 1909.”
  - HF Tercentenary Celebration Watch Fob, Patina present on front right outer edge and back left edge. Most silver plating has worn away on both sides and completely on top suspension bar. Toning present across front and back. Dark tarnish on base metal. (Box 23)
    Dual sided, silver-plated watch fob featuring image of “Half-Moon” on front and “Clermont” on back. Front reads Hudson/ Fulton/ 1609/ 1807/ 1909.” Back reads “Ter-Centenary/ Celebration/ Pat Applied For.”
  - HF Tercentenary Celebration Watch Fob #2, Nearly all silver-plating has worn away, only small spots across front and back remain. Dark tarnish on base metal. Potential small spot of rust on front left center edge. (Box 23)
  - HF Celebration Copper Half-Moon Watch Fob, Very small spots of patina on front design. Dark tarnish across front and back. Scratches across back and around front design, where fob is still attached to excess metal. (Box 23)
    Copper watch fob featuring image of Hudson’s “Half-Moon”. Lettering reads “Hudson Fulton/ Celebration/Half Moon/ New York/ 1609/ 1909.” Fob still features excess metal and was never fully cut free.
  - HF Celebration Copper Clermont Watch Fob, Tarnish across both front and back. Small spot of dark tarnish on front top left edge. Several potential spots of rust on back where metal is worn. Toning across back. Small area of toning on front bottom. (Box 23)
    Copper watch fob featuring image of Fulton’s “Clermont”. Lettering reads “Hudson Fulton/ Celebration/Clermont/ New York/ 1807/ 1909.”
  - HF Brass Half Moon Souvenir Watch Fob, Plating has worn away in very small areas around outer edge corners. (Box 23)
    Brass-plated watch fob featuring image of Hudson’s “Half-Moon”. Lettering on top banners reads “1609/ 1807/ Souvenir/ Hudson/ Fulton/ Celebration”. Remaining lettering reads “Halve Maene/ New York/ 1909.”
  - Hudson-Fulton Citizens’ Commission Medal Watch Fob, Patina present in small areas across obverse and reverse of medal. Patina also present in several areas on top suspension. (Box 23)
    Metal watch fob featuring design of Citizens’ Hudson-Fulton Commission medal. Obverse features image of Lady Columbia holding the “Half-Moon” and “Clermont” in each hand with background of NYC skyline. Edges read “Hudson-Fulton/ Celebration”. Reverse features portraits of Hudson and Fulton. Edges read “Henry Hudson 1609/ Robert Fulton 1807/ 1909”.
  - HF Celebration New York to Albany Copper Watch Fob #1-2, Tarnish across both sides. Small spots of patina along outer edges and in small areas on backs. (Box 23)
    Copper watch fob featuring portraits of Hudson and Fulton on front and images of “Half-Moon” and “Clermont” on back. Front lettering reads “Hudson-Fulton/ Celebration/ Sept. 25 to Oct. 9/ 1909”. Back lettering reads “New York to Albany/ Half Moon 1609/ Clermont 1807.”
  - N.C. Walter & Sons Silver-Plated HF Half-Moon Watch Fob, Most of silver plating has worn away, leaving only small areas on front. Tarnish across base metal. Leather strap is slightly brittle and black dye has faded. There are several cracks in top layer of leather, as well. (Box 23)
    Silver-plated watch fob featuring image of Hudson’s “half-Moon” below banner for Hudson-Fulton Celebration. Fob is suspended from leather strap with metal buckle. Maker’s mark on back for N.C. Walter & Sons, NY.
- 10. Musical Instrument - Zither, 1909; 1.33 linear feet 1 Box (Box 24)
  Commemorative musical instrument created for The 1909 Hudson-Fulton Celebration.
  - 1909 Hudson-Fulton Celebration Zither With Original Box, Outer box features several large cracks and the top layer is flaking away in several large areas. The sides of both top and bottom parts of box are very fragile and some have broken. The instrument is missing three strings on the far right. There is a large crack in the back. Inside label has begun to peel off backing. (Box 24)
    Wooden zither/Chickering harp with cherry wood stain. Bottom of front features a labelled scale for each string. Top left of instrument features a label that reads “Special/ Hudson-Fulton/ Model” below image of Hudson’s “Half-Moon.” Maker’s mark on inside cavity of instrument for Oscar Schmidt. Intricate design around center opening features images of harps and other string instrument. Outer box is black with label for Chickering harp along bottom edge of top half.
- 11. Miscellany, 1907-1909; 0.21 linear feet 1 Box (Box 25)
  Miscellaneous documents, maps, cards and souvenir items relating to The 1909 Hudson-Fulton Celebration Collection.
  - TRC Mary Powell Card #1-2, Creases throughout. (Box 25, Folder 1)
    Two small cards featuring color image of and information on “Mary Powell” ship.
  - TRC Ferryboat Jersey Card, Small tears/damage to image on top left to middle. Fraying at corners. (Box 25, Folder 1)
    Small card featuring color image of and information on “Ferryboat Jersey.”
  - TRC Half-Moon Card, Significant crease on top right corner. Large creases throughout. Several scratches over image. Significant fraying of corners and edges. Small stain on front top right. Staining over back. Paper is fragile. (Box 25, Folder 1)
    Small card featuring color image of and information on Hudson’s “Half-Moon” ship.
  - TRC Fulton’s First Experiment Card (Box 25, Folder 1)
    Small card featuring color image of and information on Fulton’s first experiment with a paddle boat.
  - TRC De Witt Clinton Card, Very faint creasing along top. (Box 25, Folder 1)
    Small card featuring color image and information on “De Witt Clinton” ship.
  - TRC War Vessel Demologos Card, Several scratched over image. Large crease across image. Fraying of edges and corners. (Box 25, Folder 1)
    Small card featuring color image of and information on “U.S. War Vessel Demologos”.
  - TRC Paragon Card, Fraying of corners and edges. Creasing along top of card and down the middle. Small stain on upper right corner. (Box 25, Folder 1)
    Small card featuring color image of and information on the ship “Paragon.”
  - TRC Isaac Newton Card, Various scratches over image. Small crease in left center of card. Staining across the back. Slight fraying of edges and corners. (Box 25, Folder 1)
    Small card featuring color image of and information on the ship “Isaac Newton.”
  - TRC Francis Skiddy Ship Card, Crease over image on bottom left. Scratches on bottom right. Fraying of corners and edges. (Box 25, Folder 1)
    Small card featuring color image of and information on the “Francis Skiddy Ship.”
  - TRC Robert Fulton Namesake Ship Card, Crease in the bottom right corner. Small stain over image on top right toward middle. Fraying of corners and edges. (Box 25, Folder 1)
    Small card featuring color image of and information on the ship “Robert Fulton.”
  - TRC North America Ship Card, Small stains on back bottom right. (Box 25, Folder 1)
    Small card featuring color image of and information on the ship “North America.”
  - Gold Hudson-Fulton Celebration Anniversary Stamp (Box 25, Folder 1)
    22karat gold replica of 2 cent “Half-Moon” and “Clermont” stamp originally made for the Hudson-Fulton Celebration. Stamp is within its original envelope.
  - Description Card for Gold HF Celebration Stamp (Box 25, Folder 1)
    Informational card on original and reproduction stamp.
  - Hudson-Fulton Celebration 25th Anniversary Envelope (Box 25, Folder 1)